Let’s say you really need
to find reliable information
about the best diet for
high blood pressure,
or heart disease,
or diabetes.
Where do you go?
Do you go to a website
sponsored by Big Pharma
that wants to sell you
pills to fix your problem?
Or, do you want
to treat the cause?
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast
with the latest peer-
reviewed research
on the best ways to eat
healthy and live longer.
Today we take a close
look at the mighty power
of vitamin C.
And we start with
the risks and benefits
of using vitamin C for
depression and anxiety.
“Emerging evidence suggests that
higher daily intake of ﬁber-rich
fruits and vegetables is associated
with lower incidences of anxiety
in adults and at the same time,
greater happiness, higher life
satisfaction, and greater
emotional well-being.”
So, “persuading people to
consume more fruits and vegetables
may not only benefit their
physical health in the long-run,
but also their mental
well-being in the short-run.”
Fruit consumption, for example,
has protective association
with leading killers like
heart disease, stroke, diabetes,
and cancer, as well as
depression. The question is why?
Several different mechanisms
have been proposed.
For example, it may be the
antioxidants and anti-inflammatory
properties of produce, scavenging
the free radicals that are
involved in some of the
inflammation associated with depression.
If that’s the case, what about
just taking vitamin C supplements?
The brain has some of the highest
levels of vitamin C in the body;
so, the thought is if
we take extra vitamin C,
it may have some sort of
therapeutic role in brain diseases,
especially given that
it’s not just an antioxidant,
but also has other critical
functions in the brain such as
helping to build
neurotransmitters like dopamine.
But you don’t know
whether it actually helps,
until you... put it to the test.
One study found a beneficial
effect of adding vitamin C as an
adjunct treatment to an
antidepressant, while another study
found no benefit from
vitamin C supplementation.
So, there are mixed results
for vitamin C and depression.
Here’s another study that
found no benefit when it came to
depression, but those
randomized to vitamin C instead of
placebo pills did show a
significant decrease in anxiety level.
And this wasn’t only
seen in this study.
The effects of oral
vitamin C supplementation
on anxiety in students:
a double-blind, randomized,
placebo-controlled trial.
High school students were
given 500mg a day or placebo.
500mg of vitamin C is
about what you’d find
in five oranges, four
yellow kiwifruit or guavas,
or one and a half
yellow bell peppers.
Within just two weeks, the vitamin C
reduced anxiety compared to
placebo, along with providing
a significant drop in heart rate.
Given these data showing
vitamin C may have
anxiety-reducing effect,
researchers sought to find out
if only a single dose could
acutely affect emotional states.
And indeed, within only two
hours of taking some C,
subjects experienced a
significant drop in anxiety
compared to placebo,
though only among those
who started out the most
anxious in the first place.
As a bonus, vitamin C
supplementation may lower
your blood pressure a
few points, but whole fruits
and vegetables can do
the same thing and may even
do it better for those
who need it the most.
As I’ve shown previously,
even just adding two servings
of fruits and vegetables a
day can have psychological
well-being benefits
within only two weeks.
And you won’t be put at risk
of kidney stones like you would
with vitamin C supplements,
though that appears to be
only a problem in men.
Here’s a fun fact.
There are now experiments
that can show
how much vitamin C our
body absorbs and excretes.
Here’s the story.
For many years, the RDA, the
recommended daily allowance
for vitamins, was just based
on preventing deficiency,
with a margin of safety,
but the miniscule amount of vitamin C,
for example, needed to avoid scurvy
is not necessarily the ideal
intake for optimal health.
So what might be the
optimal intake of vitamin C?
Let's ask the body.
How might we do that?
By seeing how much the
body absorbs and excretes.
If you swallow 15 mg of vitamin C,
which is what you would get
eating about a quarter of an orange,
your body sucks up nearly 90% of it.
But if you take a supplement
containing 1,250 mg,
your body seems to realize that's too much,
and so clamps down on absorption
at the intestinal lining level, and you
end up absorbing less than half.
So by doing experiments where
you slowly ratchet up the intake
you can see when the body
starts to say, OK, that's enough,
and that magic level of intake
appears to be about 200 mg a day.
When you take up to 200 a day
your body sucks it all up,
but above that your body tries
to block further absorption
suggesting our intestinal vitamin C
transport mechanisms have evolved
to fully absorb up to about
200 mg of vitamin C a day.
In addition, vitamin C is reabsorbed in
our kidneys back into our bloodstream
to maintain our vitamin C blood levels up
at around 70 or 80 micromoles per liter.
Which is what you reach at a vitamin C
intake of about 200 mg a day.
So even if you take 10 times as
much vitamin C supplements,
you know, 2000 mg a day, your
body will just pee and poop it out
to keep your blood levels
in that narrow range.
So based on these kind of data,
one might propose that 200 mg is
the optimal daily intake of vitamin C.
You can confirm using disease data.
At what daily intake of vitamin C is
there the lowest stroke risk, for example?
Apparently at about 200 mg a day.
While dietary vitamin C intake was
associated with lower stroke risk,
vitamin C supplements
were not,
which is consistent with
the overall body of evidence
showing that antioxidant
supplements in general
don't seem to protect against
heart attacks or strokes.
But wait...
Can you get all up to an intake of 200 mg
a day without taking supplements?
No problem.
Single servings of fruits and
vegetables may have about 50 mg each,
so a measly 5 servings
of fruits and veggies a day
could get you to
ideal blood levels.
Finally today, what
can we conclude
about the role of IV vitamin C
after 33 years of trials
involving more than
1,500 patients?
Studies in the 70s showed an
extraordinary survival gain
in terminal cancer patients
with vitamin C,
a simple, relatively
nontoxic therapy,
and so no wonder it got
a lot of attention
especially when reported by
a world-renowned scientist,
Linus Pauling,
but studies like this in the
1980s found no such benefit
and so alas they were left
with the inevitable conclusion
that the apparent
positive results
in the original study were
the product of bias
rather than treatment
effectiveness.
In the 90s though,
an alternative explanation arose.
The disappointing 80s research
only used oral vitamin C,
whereas the apparently
successful 70s experiments
also gave vitamin C
intravenously
and we didn’t realize
until the 90s
that the same dose given IV
can lead to dramatically
higher levels in
the blood stream
than if taken
orally,
So maybe high dose vitamin C
does help in terminal cancer,
but maybe only when
given intravenously.
Encouraging case reports
continue to be published.
Here there was a regression,
remission and cure
documented in individual cases
of advanced kidney cancer,
bladder cancer,
and lymphoma.
But that’s three success
stories out of how many?
If it was three
out of a hundred,
or even three out
of a thousand...well okay,
if the treatment is
sufficiently nontoxic,
but there’s evidence
that IV vitamin C
is widely used in the
alternative medicine world,
as in 86% of
practitioners surveyed.
Just those 172
practitioners alone
treated about 10,000
patients a year
And you ask the
manufacturers,
and they’re selling hundreds
of thousands of vials
of this stuff
in the U.S.
Now it’s not all being
used for cancer,
but presumably at least thousands
of cancer patients are being treated
every year with IV vitamin C,
making the publication
of three remarkable case
reports seem less impressive.
So no matter how amazing
these cases seemed,
it’s possible the cancers
just spontaneously regressed
all on their own and it
was just a coincidence
that it happened after they
were given vitamin C.
To know for sure you have
to put it to the test.
To date there have been
some small pilot studies,
and the results so far
have been disappointing.
The good news is that even
insane doses of IV vitamin C
seem remarkably safe,
but failed in this study
of two dozen patients
to demonstrate
anticancer activity.
Similar small studies
have been published
all the way through
to the present
with tantalizing but
inconclusive results.
What we do know is that the present
state of cancer treatment
is unsatisfactory.
People have this perception
that chemotherapy
will significantly enhance
their chances for a cure,
but put all our cancer-killing
chemo together
and the overall contribution
to 5-year survival
is on the
order of 2%.
All those side-effects
for 2.1%,
at a cost of maybe $100,000
per patient per year.
So it may be worth looking
deeper into therapies
like IV vitamin C.
However, the lack of
financial reward,
since vitamin C can’t be patented
and sold for $100,000,
and bias against
alternative medicine
could dissuade conventional
investigators and funding agencies
from seriously considering
this approach.
So decades later what
can we conclude?
After trials which have included
at least 1,600 patients
over 33 years, we
have to conclude...
that we still don't know
whether Vitamin C has any clinically
significant antitumor activity.
Although there is currently no
definitive evidence of benefit,
the Mayo Clinic randomized
controlled trials
did not negate the potential
benefit based on what we now know
about oral versus IV
routes of administration.
So we’re kind of
back to square one,
does it work
or not?
There are highly polarized
views on both sides,
but everyone’s working off
the same incomplete data.
What we need are carefully
controlled clinical trials.
The question is, what
do we do until then?
If it was completely nontoxic,
then one could argue-
what have you
got to lose?
But it’s not; it’s only
relatively nontoxic.
For example, there have
been rare but serious cases
of kidney injury
reported.
After all, if it’s
so safe,
why did our
bodies evolve
to so tightly control
against excess absorption?
It can also be expensive
and time-consuming.
Each infusion can cost 1 to 2 hundred
dollars out of pocket,
since insurance
doesn't pay for it.
which can be quite a boon for
alternative medicine practitioners.
About 90% of the millions
of doses of vitamin C
being dispensed are in
for-profit arrangements,
so there’s financial pressures
pushing in both directions,
for and against
this treatment.
Given the relative safety
and expense, though,
if controlled studies even
find a small benefit,
it would be
worthwhile.
And if they don’t, okay, fine,
the vitamin C question
can be put to rest
once and for all.
But in cancer treatment
we don’t have the luxury
of jettisoning possibly effective
relatively nontoxic treatments.
We should revisit
promising avenues,
without prejudice,
and with open minds.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.